Funding for this program is provided by
Additional funding provided by
The National Center for the Arts and Sciences
and the National Center for the Arts and Sciences.
is a non-profit, non-profit organization
based in the United States.
When we finished last time,
we were looking at Jon Stewart Mills' attempt
to create a program
to reply to the critics
of Bentham's utilitarianism.
In his book Utilitarianism,
Mills tries to show that critics to the contrary,
it is possible within the utilitarian framework
to distinguish between higher and lower pleasures.
It is possible to make qualitative distinctions of worth,
and we tested that idea.
With the Simpsons and the Shakespeare excerpts.
And the results of our experiment
seem to call into question
Mills' distinction.
Because a great many of you
reported that you prefer the Simpsons,
but that you still consider Shakespeare
to be the higher or the worthier.
Pleasure.
That's the dilemma
with which our experiment confronts Mill.
What about Mills' attempt to account
for the specially weighty character
of individual rights and justice
in chapter five of Utilitarianism?
He wants to say that individual rights
are worthy of special respect.
In fact, he goes so far as to say
that justice is the most sacred part
and the most incomparably binding part of morality.
But the same challenge
could be put to this part of Mills' defense.
Why is justice the chief part
and the most binding part of all morality?
Well, he says because in the long run,
if we do justice and if we respect rights,
society as a whole will be
better off in the long run.
Well, what about that?
What if we have a case where making an exception
and violating individual rights
actually will make people better off in the long run?
Is it all right then to use people?
And there's a further objection
that could be raised against
Mills' case for justice and rights.
Suppose the Utilitarianism
and the Utilitarianism of the United States
is to be respected.
Suppose the Utilitarian Calculus in the long run
works out as he says it will,
such that respecting people's rights
is a way of making everybody better off
in the long run.
Is that the right reason?
Is that the only reason to respect people?
If the doctor goes in and yanks the organs
from the healthy patient who came in for a checkup
and then he says,
well, I'm going to use him in this way,
in the long run,
more lives will be lost.
There would be adverse effects in the long run.
Eventually, people would learn about this
and would stop going in for checkups.
Is it the right reason?
Is the only reason that you as the doctor
won't yank the organs out of the healthy patient
that you think,
well, if I use him in this way,
he'll be out?
Or is there another reason,
having to do with intrinsic respect
for the person as an individual?
And if that reason matters,
then it's not so clear
that even Mill's utilitarianism
can take account of it.
Fully to examine these two worries or objections
to Mill's defense,
we need to do,
and push further,
and we need to ask,
in the case of higher or worthier pleasures,
are there theories of the good life
that can provide independent moral standards
for the worth of pleasures?
If so, what do they look like?
That's one question.
In the case of justice and rights,
if we suspect that Mill
is implicitly leaning on notions of human dignity
or respect for a person
that are not, strictly speaking, utilitarian,
we need to look to see
whether there are some stronger theories of rights
that can explain the intuition,
which even Mill shares,
the intuition that the reason
for respecting individuals and not using them
goes beyond even utility
in the long run.
Today we turn to one
of those strong theories of rights.
Strong theories of rights say
individuals matter
not just as instruments to be used
for a larger social purpose
or for the sake of maximizing utility.
Individuals are separate beings
with separate lives,
worthy of respect.
And so it's a mistake,
according to strong theories of rights,
it's a mistake
to think about justice or law
by just adding up preferences and values.
The strong rights theory we turn to today
is libertarianism.
Libertarianism takes individual rights seriously.
It's called libertarianism because it says
the fundamental individual right
is the right to liberty.
Precisely because we are separate individual beings,
we're not available
to any use
that the society might desire or devise.
Precisely because we are individual,
separate human beings,
we have a fundamental right to liberty.
And that means
a right to choose freely,
to live our lives as we please,
provided we respect other people's rights
to do the same.
That's the fundamental idea.
Robert Nozick,
one of the libertarian philosophers we read
for this course, puts it this way.
Individuals have rights
so strong and far-reaching
are these rights
that they raise the question of what,
if anything,
the state may do.
So what does libertarianism say
about the role of government
or of the state?
Well, there are three things
that most modern states do
that, on the libertarian theory of rights,
are illegitimate,
are unjust.
One of them is paternalist legislation.
That's passing laws
that protect people from themselves.
Seatbelt laws, for example,
or motorcycle helmet laws.
The libertarian says,
it may be a good thing
if people wear seatbelts,
but that should be up to them.
And the state, the government,
has no business coercing them,
us, to wear seatbelts by law.
It's coercion.
So no paternalist legislation,
number one.
Number two, no morals legislation.
Many laws try to promote
the virtue of citizens
or try to give expression
to the moral values
of the society as a whole.
Libertarians say,
that's also a violation
of the right to liberty.
Take the example of,
well, a classic example
of legislation offered
in the name of promoting morality.
Traditionally,
have been laws that prevent
sexual intimacy
between gays and lesbians.
The libertarian says,
nobody else is harmed,
nobody else's rights are violated,
so the state should get out
of the business entirely
of trying to promote virtue
or to enact morals legislation.
And the third kind of law
or policy that is ruled out
on the libertarian philosophy
is any taxation
or other policy
that serves the purpose
of redistributing income or wealth
from the rich to the poor.
Redistribution is a kind,
if you think about it,
says the libertarian,
is a kind of coercion.
What it amounts to
is theft
by the state
or by the majority,
if we're talking about a democracy,
from people who happen to do
very well and earn a lot of money.
Now,
Nozick and other libertarians
allow that there can be a minimal state
that taxes people for the sake of
what everybody needs,
the national defense,
police force,
judicial system
to enforce contracts
and property rights,
but that's it.
Now,
I want to get your reactions
to this third feature
of the libertarian view.
I want to see
who among you
agree with that idea
and who disagree and why.
But just to make it concrete
and to see what's at stake,
consider the distribution of wealth
in the United States.
The United States is among the most
inegalitarian societies
as far as the distribution of wealth,
of all the advanced democracies.
Now,
is this just
or unjust?
Well, what does the libertarian say?
The libertarian says,
you can't know just from the facts
I've just given you,
you can't know whether that distribution
is just or unjust.
You can't know just by looking at a pattern
or a distribution or a result
whether it's just or unjust.
You have to know how it came to be.
You can't just look at the end state
or the result.
You have to look at two principles.
The first he calls justice in acquisition
or in initial holdings.
And what that means simply is,
did people get the things they used
to make their money
fairly?
So we need to know
was there justice in the initial holdings?
Did they steal the land or the factory
or the goods that enabled them to make
all that money?
If not,
if they were entitled to whatever it was
that enabled them to
gather the wealth,
the first principle is met.
The second principle is,
did the distribution arise
from the operation of free consent?
People buying and trading on the market.
As you can see,
the libertarian idea of justice
corresponds to a free market
conception of justice.
Provided people got what they used
fairly, didn't steal it,
and provided the distribution results
from the free choice of individuals
buying and selling things,
the distribution is just.
And if not, it's unjust.
So let's, in order to fix ideas
for this discussion,
take an actual example.
Who's the wealthiest person
in the United States?
Wealthiest person in the world?
Bill Gates.
It is.
That's right.
Here he is.
You'd be happy too.
Now, what's his net worth?
Anybody have any idea?
That's a big number.
During the Clinton years,
remember there was a controversy,
donors, big campaign contributors
were invited to stay overnight
in the Lincoln bedroom
at the White House.
I think if you contributed $25,000 or above,
someone figured out
that the median contribution
that got you invited to stay
a night in the Lincoln bedroom,
Bill Gates could afford
to stay in the Lincoln bedroom
every night for the next 66,000 years.
Somebody else figured out
how much does he get paid
on an hourly basis?
And so they figured out
since he began Microsoft,
suppose he worked, what,
14 hours per day.
Reasonable guess.
And you calculate this net wealth.
It turns out that his rate of pay
is over $150,
not per hour,
not per minute.
$150, more than $150 per second.
Which means,
which means that if on a daily basis,
that if on his way to the office,
Gates noticed a $100 bill on the street,
it wouldn't be worth his time
to stop and pick it up.
Now, most of you will say,
someone that wealthy,
surely we can tax them
to meet the pressing needs
of people who lack an education
or lack enough to eat
or lack decent housing.
They need it more than he does.
And if you were a utilitarian,
what would you do?
What tax policy would you have?
You'd redistribute in a flash,
wouldn't you?
Because you would know,
being a good utilitarian,
that taking some,
a small amount,
he's scarcely going to notice it.
But it will make a huge improvement
in the lives and in the welfare
of those at the bottom.
But remember,
the libertarian theory says,
we can't just add up
and aggregate preferences
and satisfactions that way.
We have to respect persons,
and if he earned that money fairly,
without violating anybody else's rights,
in accordance with the two principles
of justice in acquisition
and justice in transfer,
then it would be wrong,
it would be a form of coercion
to take it away.
Michael Jordan is not as wealthy
as Bill Gates,
but he did pretty well for himself.
You want to see Michael Jordan?
There he is.
His income alone in one year
was 31 million dollars,
and then he made another 47 million dollars
in endorsements for Nike
and other companies.
So his income was,
in one year, 78 million.
To require him to pay,
let's say, a third of his earnings
to the government
to support good causes,
like food and healthcare
and housing and education for the poor,
that's coercion.
That's unjust.
That violates his rights.
And that's why redistribution is wrong.
Now, how many agree with that argument?
Agree with the libertarian argument
that redistribution for the sake of
trying to help the poor is wrong?
And how many disagree with that argument?
All right, let's begin with those who disagree.
What's wrong with the libertarian case
against redistribution?
Yes.
I think these people like Michael Jordan
have received,
we're talking about working within a society,
and they received a larger gift from the society,
and they have a larger obligation in return
to give that through redistribution.
You know, you can say that Michael Jordan
may work just as hard as someone who works
doing laundry 12 hours, 14 hours a day,
but he's receiving more.
I don't think it's fair to say that, you know,
it's all on his, you know, inherent hard work.
All right.
Let's hear from defenders of libertarianism.
Why would it be wrong in principle
to tax the rich to help the poor?
Go ahead.
My name's Joe, and I collect skateboards.
I've since bought 100 skateboards.
I live in a society of 100 people.
I'm the only one with skateboards.
Suddenly everyone decides they want a skateboard.
They come into my house, they take my,
they take 99 of my skateboards.
I think that is unjust.
Now, I think in certain circumstances,
it becomes necessary to overlook that injustice,
perhaps condone that injustice,
as in the case of the
cabin boy being killed for food.
If people are on the verge of dying,
perhaps it is necessary to overlook that injustice.
But I think it's important to keep in mind
that we're still committing injustice
by taking people's belongings or assets.
Are you saying that taxing Michael Jordan,
say, at a 33% tax rate,
for good causes,
to feed the hungry,
is theft?
I think it's unjust.
Yes, I do believe it's theft,
but perhaps it is necessary to condone that theft.
But it's theft.
Yes.
Why is it theft, Joe?
Because...
Why is it like your collection of skateboards?
It's theft because, at least in my opinion,
and by the libertarian opinion,
he earned that money fairly,
and it belongs to him.
So to take it from him is, by definition, theft.
All right, let's see if there's...
Who wants to reply to Joe?
Yes, go ahead.
I don't think this is necessarily a case
in which you have 99 skateboards
and the government...
Or you have 100 skateboards
and the government's taking 99 of them.
It's like you have more skateboards
than there are days in a year.
You have more skateboards
than you're going to be able to use
in your entire lifetime,
and the government is taking part of those.
And I think that if you're operating in a society
in which the government's...
In which the government does not have the money
to pay for the skateboards,
then you're not taking part of those.
And if the government doesn't redistribute wealth,
then that allows for people to amass so much wealth
that people who haven't started
from this very...
The equal footing in our hypothetical situation
that doesn't exist in our real society
get undercut for the rest of their lives.
So you're worried that if there isn't
some degree of redistribution,
if some are left at the bottom,
there will be no genuine equality of opportunity.
All right.
The idea that taxation is theft.
Nozick takes that point one step further.
He agrees that it's theft.
He's more demanding than Joe.
Joe says it is theft.
Maybe in an extreme case it's justified.
Maybe a parent is justified
in stealing a loaf of bread
to feed his or her hungry family.
So Joe is a...
What would you call yourself?
A compassionate quasi-libertarian?
Nozick says, if you think about it,
taxation amounts to the taking of earnings.
In other words, it means
taking the fruits of my labor.
But if the state has the right
to take my earnings or the fruits of my labor,
isn't that morally the same
as according to the state
the right to claim a portion of my labor?
So taxation actually
is morally equivalent
to forced labor.
Because forced labor
involves the taking of my leisure,
my time, my efforts,
just as taxation takes the earnings
that I make with my labor.
And so for Nozick
and for the libertarians,
taxation for redistribution is theft,
as Joe says.
But not only theft,
it's morally equivalent
to laying claim to certain hours
of a person's life and labor.
So it's morally equivalent
to forced labor.
If the state has a right
to claim the fruits of my labor,
that implies that it really
has an entitlement
to my labor itself.
And what is forced labor?
Forced labor,
Nozick points out,
is what?
Is slavery.
Because if I don't have the right,
the sole right,
to my own labor,
then that's really to say
that the government
or the political community
is a part owner in me.
And what does it mean
for the state to be a part owner in me?
If you think about it,
it means that I'm a slave,
that I don't own myself.
So what this line of reasoning brings us to
is the fundamental principle
that underlies the libertarian case for rights.
What is that principle?
It's the idea that I own myself.
It's the idea of self-possession.
If you want to take rights seriously,
if you don't want to just regard people
as collections of preferences,
the fundamental moral idea
to which you will be led
is the idea that we are the owners
or the proprietors of our own person.
And that's why
utilitarianism is so important.
utilitarianism goes wrong.
And that's why it's wrong
to yank the organs from that healthy patient.
You're acting as if
that patient belongs to you
or to the community.
But we belong to ourselves.
And that's the same reason
that it's wrong to make laws
to protect us from ourselves
or to tell us how to live,
to tell us what virtues
we should be governed by,
and that's also why it's wrong
to tax the rich,
to help the poor,
even for good causes,
even to help those who are displaced
by the Hurricane Katrina.
Ask them to give charity.
But if you tax them,
it's like forcing them to labor.
Could you tell Michael Jordan
he has to skip the next week's games
and go down to help the people
displaced by Hurricane Katrina?
Morally, it's the same.
So the stakes are very high.
So far we've heard some objections
to the libertarian argument,
but if you want to reject it,
you have to break into this chain of reasoning,
which goes,
taking my earnings is like taking my labor,
but taking my labor is making me a slave.
And if you disagree with that,
you must believe in the principle of self-possession.
Those who disagree,
gather your objections,
and we'll begin with them next time.
Anyone like to take up that point?
Yes.
I feel like when you live in a society,
you give up that right.
I mean, technically,
if I want to personally give up that right,
I can't go out and kill someone
because they offend me.
That is self-possession.
Because I live in a society,
I cannot do that.
Victoria, are you questioning
the fundamental premise of self-possession?
Yes.
I think that you don't really have self-possession
if you choose to live in a society
because you cannot just discount
the people around you.
We were talking last time about libertarianism.
I want to go back to the arguments
for and against the redistribution
of income.
But before we do that,
just one word about the minimal state.
Milton Friedman,
the libertarian economist,
he points out that many of the functions
that we take for granted
as properly belonging to government
don't.
They are paternalist.
One example he gives is social security.
He says it's a good thing
to have a social security system.
He says it's a good idea
for people to save for their retirement
during their earning years.
But it's wrong.
It's a violation of people's liberty
for the government to force everyone,
whether they want to or not,
to put aside some earnings today
for the sake of their retirement.
If people want to take the chance,
or if people want to live big today
and live a poor retirement,
that should be their choice.
They should be free to make those judgments
and take those risks.
So even social security
would still be at odds with the minimal state
that Milton Friedman argued for.
It's sometimes thought that
collective goods like police protection
and fire protection
will inevitably create the problem
of free riders,
unless they're publicly provided.
But there are ways
to prevent free riders.
There are ways to restrict
even seemingly collective goods
like fire protection.
I read an article a while back
about a private fire company,
the Salem Fire Corporation in Arkansas.
You can sign up with the Salem Fire Corporation,
pay a yearly subscription fee,
and if your house catches on fire,
they will come and put out the fire.
But they won't put out everybody's fire.
They will only put it out
if it's a fire in the home of a subscriber,
or if it starts to spread
and to threaten the home of a subscriber.
The newspaper article told the story
of a homeowner who had subscribed
to this company in the past,
but failed to renew his subscription.
His house caught on fire.
The Salem Fire Corporation showed up with its trucks
and watched the house burn,
just making sure that it didn't spread.
The fire chief was asked,
well, he wasn't exactly the fire chief,
I guess he was the CEO.
He was asked,
how can you stand by with fire equipment
and allow a person's home to burn?
He replied,
once we verified there was no danger
to a member's property,
we had no choice but to back off
according to our rules.
If we responded to all fires, he said,
there would be no incentive to subscribe.
The homeowner, in this case,
tried to renew his subscription
at the scene of the fire,
but the head of the company refused.
You can't wreck your car, he said,
and then buy insurance for it.
He said,
I'll buy it later.
So even public goods that we take for granted
as being within the proper province of government
can, many of them, in principle,
be isolated, made exclusive to those who pay.
That's all to do with the question of collective goods
and the libertarian's injunction against paternalism.
But let's go back now
to the arguments about redistribution.
Now, underlying the libertarian's case
for the minimal state
is a worry about coercion.
But what's wrong with coercion?
The libertarian offers this answer.
To coerce someone,
to use some person
for the sake of the general welfare,
is wrong
because it calls into question
the fundamental fact
that we own ourselves,
the fundamental moral fact
of self-possession or self-ownership.
The libertarian's argument against redistribution
begins with this fundamental idea
that we own ourselves.
Nozick says
that if
the society as a whole
can go to Bill Gates
or go to Michael Jordan
and tax away a portion of their wealth,
what the society is really asserting
is a collective property right
in Bill Gates
or in Michael Jordan.
But that violates
the fundamental principle
that we belong to ourselves.
Now, we've already heard
a number of objections
to the libertarian argument.
What I would like to do today
is to give
the libertarians among us
a chance to answer the objections
that have been raised.
And some have been,
some have already identified themselves
and have agreed to come and make the case
for libertarianism,
to reply to the objections
that have been raised.
So, raise your hand
if you are among the libertarians
who's prepared to stand up
for the theory
and respond to the objections.
You are?
Alex Harris,
who's been a star on the web blog.
All right, Alex, come here.
Stand up, come.
We'll create a libertarian corner over here.
And who else?
Other libertarians?
Who will join?
What's your name?
John?
John Sheffield.
Who else wants to join?
Other brave libertarians
who are prepared to take on...
Yes.
What's your name?
Julia Roto.
Julia, come join us over there.
Now, while the...
While Team Libertarian...
Julia, John, Alex.
While Team Libertarian is gathering over there,
let me just summarize
the main objections that I've heard
in class and on the website.
Objection number one.
And here, I'll come down to...
I want to talk to Team Libertarian over here.
So, objection number one
is that
the poor need the money more.
That's an obvious objection.
A lot more than...
Thanks.
Than do Bill Gates and Michael Jordan.
Objection number two.
It's not really slavery to tax.
Because,
at least in a democratic society,
it's not a slave holder.
It's...
It's Congress.
It's a democratic...
You're smiling, Alex, already.
You're confident you can reply to all of these?
So, taxation by consent of the governed
is not coerced.
Third, some people have said,
don't the successful, like Gates,
owe a debt to society for their success
that they repay by paying taxes?
Who wants to respond to the first one?
The poor need the money more.
All right.
And you're?
John.
John. All right, John.
Let's see. Here, I'll hold it.
All right.
The poor need the money more.
That's quite obvious.
I could use the money.
You know, I certainly wouldn't mind
if Bill Gates gave me a million dollars.
I mean, I'd take a thousand.
But at some point,
you have to understand
that the benefits of redistribution of wealth
don't justify the initial violation
of the property right.
If you look at the argument,
the poor need the money more,
at no point in that argument
do you contradict the fact
that we've extrapolated from agreed upon principles
to the fact that the poor need the money more.
And that's not the case.
I think that the argument
is that the poor need the money more.
And that's not the case.
I think that the argument
is that the poor need the money more.
And that's not the case.
I think that the argument
is that the poor need the money more.
And that's not the case.
I think that the argument
is that the poor need the money more.
And that's not the case.
As an independent media,
I don't see it as Yoursence.
I think that the argument
is that the poor need the money more.
exists because it is Fake.
Itishing is consistent.
It's not a personal choice
that you would think
if you wanted to serve
the entire population in a property to use.
So now I have a idea
that a small device
from which you
can take and enjoy
the cocoa
better than your friends,
Bill Gates can give to charity if he wants to.
Right.
But it would still be wrong to coerce him.
Exactly.
To meet the needs of the poor.
Are the two of you happy with that reply?
Anything to add?
All right.
Go ahead, Julie.
I think, Julia, yes.
I think I could also add, I guess
I could add that there's a difference between needing
something and deserving something.
I mean, in a ideal society, everyone's needs
will be met, but here we're arguing what do
we deserve as a society.
And the poor don't deserve the benefits that
would flow from taxing Michael Jordan to help
them.
Based on what we've come up with here,
I don't think you deserve something like that.
Let me push you a little bit on that, Julia.
The victims of Hurricane Katrina
are in desperate need of help.
Would you say that they don't deserve
help that would come from the federal government
through taxation?
Okay.
That's a difficult question.
I think this is a case
where they need help, not deserve it.
But I think, again, if you hit a
certain level of requirements to reach sustenance, you're
going to need help.
Like if you don't have food or a
place to live, that's a case of need.
So need is one thing and desert is another.
Exactly.
All right.
Who would like to reply?
Yes.
Going back to the first point that he
made about the property rights of the individual,
the property rights are established and enforced
by the government, which is a democratic government,
and we have representatives who enforce those rights.
If you live in a
society that operates under those rules,
then it should be a
society that is a democratic society.
It should be up to the government to
decide how those resources that come out through
taxation are distributed because it is
through the consent of the government.
If you disagree with it, you don't have
to live in that society where that operates.
All right.
Good.
And tell me your name.
Raul.
Raul is pointing out, actually Raul is invoking
point number two, if the taxation is by the
consent of the governed, it's not coerced.
It's not a government.
It's legitimate.
Bill Gates and Michael Jordan
are citizens of the United States.
They get to vote for Congress.
They get to vote their
policy convictions, just like everybody else.
Who would like to take that one on?
John.
All right.
Basically, what the libertarians are objecting to in
this case is the middle 80 percent deciding
what the top 10 percent are
doing for the bottom 10 percent.
That's the only thing.
Wait, wait, wait, wait, wait, John.
I was excited.
Don't you believe in democracy?
Well, right, but at some point...
Don't you believe in the...
I mean, you say 80 percent, 10 percent majority.
Majority rule is what?
The majority.
Exactly.
Exactly, but...
In a democracy.
Aren't you for democracy?
Yes, I'm for democracy, but...
Hang on, hang on, hang on.
Democracy and mob rule aren't the same thing.
Mob rule?
Mob rule.
Exactly.
But in an open society, you have
a recourse to address that through your representatives.
And if the majority of the consent of
those who are governed doesn't agree with you, then...
I'm sorry.
If the majority of the consent of those
who are governed doesn't agree with you, then
you know you're choosing to live in this society,
and you have to operate under what the majority
of society concludes.
All right, Alex, on democracy.
Democracy, what about that?
The fact that I have won 500,000th of
a vote for one representative in Congress is not
the same thing as my having the ability to
decide for myself how to use my property rights.
I'm a drop in the bucket.
And well...
You might lose the vote.
Exactly.
And they might take...
And I will.
I mean, I don't have the decision right
now of whether or not to pay taxes.
If I don't, I get locked in jail.
Or they tell me to get out of the country.
But Alex, Alex, let me make a small
case for democracy and see what you would say.
Why can't you...
We live in a democratic society with freedom of speech.
Why can't you take to the hustings?
Persuade your fellow citizens.
Persuade your fellow citizens that taxation is
unjust and try to get a majority.
I don't think that people should be...
Should have to convince 280 million others
simply in order to exercise their own rights,
in order to not have their self-ownership violated.
I think people should be able to do
that without having to convince 280 million people.
Does that mean you're against democracy as a whole?
I...
No.
I just believe in a very limited form
of democracy whereby we have a constitution that severely
limits the scope of what decisions can be made.
What are the options?
What are the unicorns?
What can we do?
What are the social
systems that make decisions democratically?
I don't know.
I haven't seen any of these.
I don't know if there were any other questions that
I had for you that I would add or try
to get to.
Yeah, and I just...
I don't know if there were any other questions.
I don't know if there's anything else I
would add, but I don't think these positions can
be made democratically.
All right.
So, you're saying that the democracy
is fine, except where fundamental rights are
involved.
And I think you could win
if you're going on the hustings.
Let me add one element
to the argument you might make.
Maybe you could say, put
aside the economic debates, taxation.
Suppose the individual right to
religious liberty were at stake.
liberty were at stake. Then, Alex, you could
say on the hustings, surely you would all agree
that we shouldn't put the right
to individual liberty up to a vote?
Yeah, that's exactly right. And that's why
we have constitutional amendments and why we make
it so hard to amend our constitution. So
you would say that the right to private property,
the right of Michael Jordan to keep all the
money he makes, at least to protect it from
redistribution, is the same kind of right with the
same kind of weight as the right to freedom
of speech, the right to religious liberty,
rights that should trump what the majority wants.
Absolutely. The reason why we have a right
to free speech is because we have a right
to own ourselves, to exercise our
voice in any way that we choose.
All right.
Good. All right. So there we are. Who
would like to respond to that argument about
democracy being... Okay, up there. Stand up.
I think comparing religion, economics, it's not the
same thing. The reason why Bill Gates was able
to make so much money is because we live
in an economically and socially stable society. And if
the government didn't provide for the poorest 10%,
as you say, through taxation, then we would need
more money for police to...
Right.
...prevent crime. And so either way, there
would be more taxes taken away to provide
what you guys call the
necessary things that the government provides.
What's your name?
Anna.
Anna, let me ask you this. Why is
the fundamental right to religious liberty different from
the right Alex asserts as a fundamental right
to private property and to keep our free speech?
Well, I think...
You're going to do a good job.
Okay.
I'll stop.
All right.
what I earn. What's the difference between the
two? Because you wouldn't have, you wouldn't be
able to make money. You wouldn't be able to
own property if there wasn't a socially, like if
society wasn't stable. And that's completely
different from religion. That's like something
personal, something that you can practice on your
own in your own home. Whereas like me practicing,
my religion is not going to affect the
next person. But if I'm poor and I'm desperate,
um, like I might commit a crime to
feed my family and that can affect others.
Okay, good. Thank you. Would it be wrong
for someone to steal a loaf of bread
to feed his starving family? Is
that wrong? I believe that it is.
Let's take, let's take a quick poll of the
three of you. You say yes, it is wrong.
It violates property rights. It's wrong.
Even to save a starving family.
I mean, there, there,
there are definitely other ways around that. And by
justifying, no, hang on, hang on before you laugh
at me. Um, that didn't work before, before
justifying the, the act of stealing, you have
to look at violating the right that we've
already agreed exists of the right of self-possession and
the possession of, I mean, your own things.
We agree on property rights. We agree at stealing.
So property rights is not the issue.
All right. But so why is it,
why is it wrong to steal
even to feed your starving family?
Sort of the original argument that I made in
the very, in the very first question you asked,
the benefits of an action don't
justify, don't make the action just.
Do you want, what would you say, Julia? Is it all
right to steal a loaf of bread to feed a starving
family or to steal a drug that
your, your child needs to, to survive?
I think I'm okay with that, honestly.
Um, even from a libertarian standpoint, I think
that, okay, saying that you can just take
money arbitrarily from people who have a lot
to, to go to this pool of people who
need it, but you have an individual who's acting
on their own behalf to kind of save themselves.
I mean, I think you said they, from the idea
of like self-possession, they're also in
charge of protecting themselves and keeping themselves
alive. So therefore, even from a
libertarian standpoint, that might be okay.
All right. That's good. That's good. All right.
What about, what about number three up here?
Isn't it the case that the successful, the
wealthy owe a debt? They didn't do that all
by themselves. They had to cooperate with other
people that they, they owe a debt to
society and that that's expressed in taxation.
You want to take that on, Julie?
Okay. This one, um, I believe that there is
not a debt to society in the sense that how
did these people become wealthy? They did
something that society valued highly. I think
that society has already been
giving, been fighting for them.
Uh, if anything, I think it's, it's,
everything's canceled out. They provided a service to
society and society responded by
somehow they got their wealth.
Well, so be concrete in the case of
Michael Jordan, some, I mean, to illustrate your point,
there were people who helped him make
the money, the teammates, the coach, people who
taught him how to play, but they've, you're
saying, but they've all been paid for their
services. Exactly. And society derived a lot of benefit
and pleasure from watching Michael Jordan.
Exactly. And society derived a lot of
benefit and pleasure from watching Michael Jordan.
Um, I think that that's how
he paid his debt to society.
All right. Good. Who would anyone
like to take up that point? Yes.
Um, I think that there's a problem here
with, that we're assuming that a person has
self possession when they live in a society. I
feel like when you live in a society, you
give up that right. I mean, technically, if
I want to personally go out and kill someone
because they offend me, that is self possession.
But because I live in a society, I cannot
do that. I think it's kind of about the
right to take up that right. I think that's kind
kind of equivalent to say, because I have more
money, I have resources that can save people's lives.
Is it not okay for the
government to take that from me?
It's self-possession only to a certain
extent because I'm living in a society
where I have to take
account of the people around me.
So are you questioning, what's your name?
Victoria.
Victoria, are you questioning
the fundamental premise of self-possession?
Yes.
I think that you don't really have self-possession
if you choose to live in a society
because you cannot just discount the people around you.
All right, I want to quickly get the
response of the libertarian team to the last point.
The last point builds on, well, maybe it
builds on Victoria's suggestion that we don't own ourselves
because it says that Bill Gates is
wealthy, that Michael Jordan makes a huge income.
Isn't wholly their own doing.
It's the product of a lot of luck.
And so we can't claim that they
morally deserve all the money they make.
Who wants to reply to that?
Alex?
You certainly could make the case that it is not,
their wealth is not appropriate to the goodness in their hearts,
but that's not really the morally relevant issue.
The point is that they have received what
they have through the free exchange of people
who have given them their holdings, usually
in exchange for providing some other service.
Good enough.
I want to try to sum up.
I want to try to sum
up what we've learned from this discussion.
But first, let's thank John, Alex, and
Julia for an excellent, a really wonderful job.
Thank you.
Toward the end of the discussion just now,
Victoria challenged the premise of this line of reasoning,
this libertarian logic.
Maybe, she suggested, we don't own ourselves after all.
Maybe.
If you reject the libertarian case against redistribution,
there would seem to be an incentive
to break into the libertarian line of reasoning
at the earliest, at the most modest level,
which is why a lot of people disputed
that taxation is morally equivalent to forced labor.
But what about the big claim, the
premise, the big idea underlying the libertarian argument?
Is it true that we own ourselves, or can we do
without that idea and still avoid what libertarians want to avoid,
creating a society and an account of justice
where some people,
can be just used for
the sake of other people's welfare,
or even for the sake of the general good?
Libertarians combat the utilitarian idea of using people
as means for the collective happiness by saying the way
to put a stop to that utilitarian logic of using persons
is to resort to the intuitively present.
So, what does that mean?
It means that we are the
proprietors of our own personal rights.
That's the very powerful idea that we
are the proprietors of our own person.
That's Alex and Julia and John and Robert Nozick.
What are the consequences for a theory
of justice and an account of rights
of calling into question the idea of self-possession?
Does it mean that we're back to utilitarianism
and using people and aggregating preferences
and pushing the fat man off the bridge?
Nozick doesn't himself fully
develop the idea of self-possession.
He borrows it from an earlier philosopher, John Locke.
John Locke accounted for the rise of private property
from the state of nature
by a chain of reasoning very similar to
the one that Nozick and the libertarians use.
John Locke said,
private property arises
because when we mix our labor
with things,
unowned things,
we come to acquire a property right in those things.
And the reason?
The reason is that we own our own labor.
And the reason for that?
We are the proprietors, the owners of our own person.
And so in order to examine
the moral force of the
libertarian claim that we own ourselves,
we need to turn to
the English political philosopher John Locke
and examine his account of private property
and self-possession.
And that's what we'll do next time.
So I think we should do just that,
or instead of slaying all the right topics
and trying to eliminate the
ties of origin and opposite diseases
in that free and safe system
for all communities,
we need to exonerate this crisis
and re занy travel and complete work
to find the one driving this powerful urge
for self-possession.
And so now everybody prefer
to move these politicians about
even faster than ever in their five years.
Funding for this program is provided by...
Additional funding provided by...